A Guide to the Papers of Frank Bane 1919-1971
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Frank Bane 1919-1971
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7280-a
This collection consists of approximately 5500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the University on July 29, 1975 by Frank Bane, 2701 Connecticut Avenue, N. W., Apartment 604, Washington, D.C. 20008.
Biographical/Historical Information
Frank Bane was born in Smithfield, Virginia, April 7, 1893. His father was Charles Lee Bane, and his mother Carrie Howard (Buckner) Bane. He graduated with an A.B. from Randolph-Macon College in 1914 and did graduate work at Columbia University in 1914-15. In 1917-18 Bane served as a cadet-pilot with the United States Army Air Corps. He married Mary Greyson Hoofnagle of Ashland, Virgiia, August 14, 1919. They had two children: Mary Clark and Frank.
Bane assumed the first of a long series of public administrative positions when he was appointed secretary of the Virginia State Board of Charities and Correction in 1920. He was successively Director of Public Welfare in Knoxville, Tennessee (1923-26); Commissioner of Public Welfare in Virginia (1926-32); and Director of the American Public Welfare Association (1932-35). In 1935 he became the first Executive Director of the Federal Social Security Board, and in 1938 Executive Director of the Council of State Governments and Secretary of the Governor's Conference. During World War II, Bane served as Director of the Division of State and Local Cooperation, Advisory Commission to the Council of National Defense (1940-41) and Director of Field Operations, Office of Price Administration (1941-42). Following the war Bane resumed his post with the Council of State Governments. In 1959 President Eisenhower appointed Bane first Chairman of the Advisory Commission on Inter-Governmental Relations, a position he held until he retired in 1966. Among the professional organizations to which he belonged were the American Science Association, the National Municipal Association, the American Association of Social Work, the National Institute of Social Sciences and Phi Kappa Sigma.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Frank Bane in this supplement to collection #7280 number ca. 5500 items (5.6 shelf feet) for the years 1919(1936-1966)1971, and consist largely of professional and personal correspondence; numerous articles, speeches and reports prepared by Mr. Bane; and tax, financial and real estate records.
Among the noteworthy figures with whom Bane corresponded in the 1940s and early 1950s are Thomas Dewey, Harry Hopkins, Robert Hutchins, Louis Brownlow, Charles Merriam, Harold Stassen, and Aubrey Williams. In addition to Bane's correspondence and his own writings, the collection includes articles by Adlai Stevenson (located in the folder labeled "Miscellaneous Materials for Articles and Speeches"), and separate folders of speeches and articles by Beardsley Ruml and Charles Merriam.
Included in the correspondence are not only folders for specific individuals, but also for various organizations and conferences, including the American Public Welfare Association, the Council on Inter- Governmental Relations, the National Committee for Mental Hygiene, the Office of Civilian Defense, the Office of Price Administration, and the Social Security Board. The latter htree folders are filed under "Frank Bane--Personal," as is a folder on the Little Rock, Arkansas integration confrontation of 1957.
Following the series of folders devoted to articles and speeches are folders of Bane's poems, stories and favorite quotations, and a "confidential estimate of the 1947-48 Fiscal Year National Budget." Of specials note among the more recent materials are: two history projects in which Bane participated as subject, one at the University of California and one at Columbia University; his lecture notes and miscellaneous materials from his visiting professorship at the University of California; a memorial article on Aubrey William; proceedings of the Advisory Commission on Inter-Governmental Relations; Bane's recommendation concerning restructuring the Commerce Department and revamping national transportation policy; copies of a one page vita of Bane's life and career, filed under "Biography"; photographs; and a 1959 mailing list.
Arrangement
The original organization of the papers as they were received has been preserved. The Bane papers are divided sequentially into three rough, overlapping chronological periods.
The first portion of the collection includes an extensive, alphabetically arranged correspondence file stretching from the mid 1930s through the early 1950s, followed by Frank Bane's articles and speeches, 1935 through 1958, in chronological order and newspaper clippings, 1939 to 1958, in chronological order.
The second portion of the collection contains, first, Frank Bane's personal and professional correspondence, 1953 to 1958, in alphabetical order, and second, tax, real estate and income records, 1938 to 1958, in chronological order.
The third portion of the collection is made up of Frank Bane's recent correspondence, 1959 to 1966, arranged alphabetically, followed by a number of Bane's major studies and reports from the 1960s, materials relating to bane's visiting professorship at the University of California, and other miscellaneous papers.
Contents List
- Correspondence - A Miscellaneous 1943-1953 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Abbott, Edith 1943-1950 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Altmeyer, Arthur J. 1941-1955 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - American Public Welfare Association 1951-1953 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - B Miscellaneous 1943-1951 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Bane, Clark 1937-1953 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Congratulations received for Appointment to Executive Directorship of Council of State Governments (CSG) 1938 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal 1939-1942 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal 1940-1950 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal - Office of Civilian Defense 1941 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal - Office of Price Administration 1941-1942 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal 1942 (Box 2)
  Includes information on the Council of State Governments, Newspaper Clippings
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  Includes a compilation of the Social Security Laws, Resolutions of Hearings and Conferences on Unemployment Compensation
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Personal 1957 (Box 2)
  The "Little Rock FIle", including press releases, statements, newspaper clippings
- Correspondence - Bane, Mrs. Frank 1938-1950 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Bane, Frank, Jr. 1941-1952 (Box 2)
  Includes Frank Jr's "Life Story"
- Correspondence - Baruch, Ismar 1940-1949 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Beeler, Roy H. 1946-1949 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Blandford, Paul S. 1940-1945 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Breckinridge, Sophonisba P. 1944-1948 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Broughton, J. Melville 1943-1949 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Brownlow, Louis 1934-1954 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - C Miscellaneous 1938-1951 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Cessna, Ralph 1942-1944 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Collins, Jerome A. 1945-1947 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Corson, John L. 1943-1955 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Council on Intergovernmental Relations 1941-1948 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Cross, Tom Peete 1943-1951 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - D Miscellaneous 1943-1949 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Daniels, Jonathan 1943-1948 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Dewey, Thomas E. 1950-1952 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Dey, William W. 1945 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Dill, William L. 1943-1949 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Dixon, Frank M. 1941-1950 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Dunn, Loula 1943-1955 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - E Miscellaneous 1944-1949 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - F Miscellaneous 1943-1950 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - G Miscellaneous 1943-1948 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Gary, J. Vaughan 1943-1945 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - L.L. Gravely Family 1942-1951 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Graves, Richard 1945-1948 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Griswold, Dwight 1947 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - H Miscellaneous 1936-1952 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Harman, Minnie 1947 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Harris, Alexander 1942-1947 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Harris, Joseph P. and Polly 1940-1949 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Hartshorne, Richard 1940-1949 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Hatcher, Samuel C. 1943-1950 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Heer, Clarence 1943-1953 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Heizer, Mabel S. 1943-1954 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Henderson, Leon 1942-1952 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Hoehler, Fred K. 1941-1949 (Box 3)
- Correspondence - Hopkins, Harry L. 1944-1947 (Box 3)
  Includes a special feature on Hopkins in Look Magazine
- Correspondence - Hutchins, Robert 1943-1949 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - J Miscellaneous 1940-1951 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Jeter, Helen 1940-1954 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - K Miscellaneous 1943-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - L Miscellaneous 1940-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Lane, William Preston, Jr. 1947-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Lawrence, Frank E. 1940 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Leet, Glen 1936-1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Lehman, Herbert H. 1943-1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Low, Josiah O. 1944-1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - M Miscellaneous 1940-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Martin, Edward 1944-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - May, Geoffrey 1949 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Merriam, Charles E. 1943-1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Moffett, Guy 1929-1949 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Mulliner, Maurine 1940-1954 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - Mc Miscellaneous 1925-1953 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - McKibbin, George 1943-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - N Miscellaneous 1924-1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - National Committee for Mental Hygiene 1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - National Conference on Aging 1950 (Box 4)
  Includes summary report
- Correspondence - Neely, Frank 1943-1952 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - New Jersey Welfar Study 1949 (Box 5)
  Includes report
- Correspondence - Newstadt, Richard 1943-1946 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - O Miscellaneous 1940-1953 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Ogburn, William F. 1940-1944 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - P Miscellaneous 1925-1953 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Peterson, Val 1950-1953 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Pierce, Anne and Bessie 1950-1952 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Pollard, Mrs. John G. 1939-1950 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Q Miscellaneous 1951 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - R Miscellaneous 1923-1952 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Randolph-Macon College 1919-1950 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Reeves, H. Clyde 1945-1947 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Rickey, Mrs. Orland D. and Louise 1940-1941 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - Ruml, Beardsley 1942-1954 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - S Miscellaneous 1924-1953 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Saltonstall, Everett 1944-1949 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Satterfield, Mrs. Dave 1940-1950 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Scott, Mrs. J.J. 1941-1951 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Shelley, Will, Aunt Gertrude, Robert 1944-1948 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Smith, Harold D. 1941-1947 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Stark, Lloyd C. 1941-9147 (Box 6)
  Includes newspaper clippings
- Correspondence - Stassen, Harold E. 1943-1949 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Stewart, Woodfill W. 1947-1951 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Stokes, Tom 1943-1951 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - T Miscellaneous 1938-1953 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Thomas, Fay 1944-1951 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Tinsdale, Keith 1942-1951 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Turner, Ellwood J. 1940-1947 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - U, V Miscellaneous 1941-1947 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Virginia 1924-1926 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - W Miscellaneous 1941-1952 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - War Production Board 1945 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Webb, James E. 1948-1950 (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Weigel, John C. 1942-1951 (Box 7)
- Correspondence - White, Leonard D. 1943-1948 (Box 7)
- Correspondence - Williams, Aubrey 1943-1952 (Box 7)
- Correspondence - Winant, John Gilbert 1937-1952 (Box 7)
- Correspondence - Women's Foundation Community Service Committee 1945 (Box 7)
- Correspondence - X, Y, Z Miscellaneous 1943-1952 (Box 7)
- Organizational Charts and Maps - Social Security Board 1941-1942 (Box 7)
- Index of Frank Bane's articles and speeches 1931-1946 (Box 7)
- Articles, speeches and comments on Social Security 1935-1936 (Box 7)
- Articles and speeches - Generally about Social Security 1935-1936 (Box 7)
- Articles and speeches 1937 (Box 7)
- Articles and speeches 1938-1939 (Box 8)
- Frank Bane's 1st report to the Council of State Governments General Assembly 1938 (Box 8)
- Frank Bane's report to Council of State Governments Board of Managers 1939 (Box 8)
- Articles and speeches 1940-1947, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Articles and speeches 1951 Feb 13 (Box 8)
  Illinois Legislature Dinner Meeting
- Articles and speeches 1953 June 19 (Box 8)
  Today's Challenge to State Government, given before the National Association of tax Administrators
- Articles and speeches 1953 Aug. 10 (Box 8)
  Education and State Government, given at the Midwest Administration Center's conference on developing public understanding and responsibility for education
- Articles and speeches 1953 (Box 8)
  Federal-State Relations: A New Look American Public Welfare Association, includes other conference materials as well
- Articles and speeches 1954 March 11 (Box 9)
  Louisiana Department of Public Welfare
- Articles and speeches 1954 March 23 (Box 9)
  Arkansas State Conference for Social Work
- Articles and speeches 1954 May 26 (Box 9)
  Frank Bane's comments at the Midwestern Regional Conference
- Articles and speeches 1954 Nov. 16 (Box 9)
  Government Control of State-Supported Institutions, given before the Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions
- Articles and speeches 1955 May 19 (Box 9)
  Obstacles in Obtaining Additional State Revenues, given at Wisconsin Chamber of Commerce
- Articles and speeches 1955 Oct. 6 (Box 9)
  What is a Good Community? given at the New Mexico Conference on Social Welfare
- Articles and speeches 1955 Dec. 2 (Box 9)
  American Public Welfare Banquet (Silver Anniversary)
- Articles and speeches 1956-1957, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Articles and speeches 1958 March 18 (Box 9)
  Administrative Leadership, given at the Alabama Public Administration Training Institute
- Articles and speeches 1958 May 6 (Box 9)
  Leadership in the Randolph-Macon Tradition, given at Randolph-Macon
- Articles and speeches 1958 May 12 (Box 9)
  Federal-State Relations, given at the National Conference on Social Welfare
- Stories 1942-1957 (Box 9)
  includes briefer quotes and poems
- Poems 1943-1955 (Box 9)
- Articles and speeches of Beardsley Ruml 1943-1957 (Box 9)
- Articles and speeches of Charles Merriam 1943-1957 (Box 9)
- A Memorial to Justice Brandeis, Article on Jackson and Roosevelt: A Comparisonn. d. (Box 9)
- A confidential estimate of the 1947-48 Fiscal Year National Budget 1946 (Box 9)
- Articles, reprints, and speeches 1943-1957 (Box 10)
  Miscellaneous materials by various authors, including Adlai Stevenson
- Clippings 1926-1958 (Box 10)
  variety of newspaper and magazine news articles and opinion pieces about Bane
- Miscellaneous speech material 1929-1958 (Box 10)
  Includes numerous addresses by other people, notes for Bane's own speeches
- Clippings - World War II 1939-1942 (Box 10)
  Includes an edition of Facts in Review, with the authorized translation of a Hitler speech
- Clippings - Office of Civilian Defense 1941-1942 (Box 10)
- Clippings - Office of Price Administration 1941-1942 (Box 10)
- Clippings - National Council Of Defense 1941-1942 (Box 10)
- Clippings - Council of State Governments and Governors' Conference 1939-1942 (Box 10)
- Clippings - World War II, International 1939-1943 (Box 11)
- Clippings - Miscellaneous 1939-1947 (Box 11)
  Mainly editorials
- Frank Bane - Personal Correspondence, A - K 1953-1958, 9 folders (Box 11)
- Frank Bane - Personal Correspondence, L - Z 1953-1958, 9 folders (Box 12)
- Income Tax Returns 1932-1942, 6 folders (Box 12)
- Estimated Income Tax 1943 (Box 12)
- Final Income Tax Return 1943 (Box 12)
- Estimated Income Tax 1944 (Box 12)
- Final Income Tax Return 1944 (Box 12)
- Estimated Income Tax 1945 (Box 12)
- Final Income Tax Return 1945 (Box 13)
- Richmond Property - Sale, Income Tax 1945 1945 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1946 (Box 13)
- Property Depreciation, Income Tax 1928-1944 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1946 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1947 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1947 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1948 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1948 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1949 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1949 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1950 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1950 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1951 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1951 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1952 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1952 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1953 (Box 13)
- Final Income Tax Return 1953 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1954 (Box 13)
- Income Tax 1954 (Box 13)
- Estimated Income Tax 1955 (Box 13)
- Income Tax 1955; Estimate 1956 1955-1956 (Box 13)
- Income Tax 1956; Estimate for 1957 1956-1957 (Box 13)
- Income Tax 1958 (Box 13)
- Virginia Taxes - Personal and Property 1928-1957 (Box 13)
- Richmond, Virginia, Real Estate - Taxes 1935-1943 (Box 13)
  Used on Income Tax Returns
- Ashland Property Sale (Income Tax 1946) 1946 (Box 14)
- Ashland, Virginia, Real Estate Statements 1936-1946 (Box 14)
  From Real Estate Agent used on Income Tax Returns
- Ashland, Virginia, Real Estate - Taxes 1936-1945 (Box 14)
- Ashland, Virginia, Real Estate - Financing 1936-1945 (Box 14)
- Recent Correspondence - A - F 1959-1966, 6 folders (Box 14)
- Recent Correspondence - G - Z 1959-1966, 16 folders (Box 15)
- Correspondence - University of Califormia, Berkeley 1964-1965 (Box 15)
- Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations 1971 (Box 15)
  Appearance before Senate and House Committees
- Mailing List 1959 (Box 15)
- Civil Service, Social Security Payment Records 1959-1966 (Box 15)
- Commerce Department project 1964 (Box 16)
  Contains proposals for Administrative Reorganization
- Transportation Study 1961 (Box 16)
- Louis Brownlow Memorial Fund Committee 1966 (Box 16)
- Aubrey Williams Article 1965 (Box 16)
- Biography 1960 (Box 16)
- Clippings 1963-1965 (Box 16)
- Photographs 1961 (Box 16)
- Medicare Study 1968 (Box 16)
  Includes reports, administrative confidential statements, biographical sketch of consultants
- Reports by Frank Bane on the Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations 1965-1966 (Box 16)
- Oral History Project, Columbia University 1965 (Box 16)
  The Social Security Project
- Oral History Project, University of California 1967 (Box 17)
  Preparing for a Career
- Lecture Notes - University of California 1964-1965 (Box 17)
- Booklet entitled The President's Camp on the Rapidann. d. (Box 17)
- Edition of Saturday Review1965 (Box 17)
  Contains article entitled What Happened at Berkeley, by James Cass
- Lists 1957-1958 (Box 17)
  Subheadings relate to Governors Boards of Managers, a Federal-State Action Committee
- Article 1967 (Box 17)
  Local Government: The Next Half Century in Institute of Government Newsletter, University of Virginia